<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOD - How to Interpret This Consists Of</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The 'This Consists Of' Section of the Tactic Reference">
            <p>When SOD starts up, your strategy file is checked to make sure it will work. Only certain items are
                allowed in certain places, so you have to be careful when creating or editing a strategy file.</p>
            <p>The 'This Consists Of' section of the Tactic Reference describes what should go where. We explain what the
                pieces are in terms of XML. If you don't know anything about XML, we recommend that you read our <a
                href="../xmlIntro.html">introduction</a> before reading this page any further.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="A Basic Example">
            <p>This the 'This consists of' section of the <a href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html">origin point
                distance</a> tactic.</p>
            <div id="contained">
                <p> &lt;<a href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html"
                    title="Distance range from a fixed point">originPointDistance</a>&gt; <div>
                        <div id="group"> &lt;latitude&gt;<b>
                                <a href="datatypes/DoubleDatatype.html">double</a>
                            </b>&lt;/latitude&gt; <div/> &lt;longitude&gt;<b>
                                <a href="datatypes/DoubleDatatype.html">double</a>
                            </b>&lt;/longitude&gt; <div/>
                            <a href="base/include/range/range.html" title="A range of lengths">range</a>
                            <div/>
                        </div>
                    </div> &lt;/<a href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html" title="Distance range from a fixed point">originPointDistance</a>&gt;<div/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <section name="The containing originPointDistance tag">
                <p>The first line shows the start tag &lt;originPointDistance&gt; . This means that at this
                    point in the strategy file (ie every place in the 'Places containing this' section) the element
                    originPointDistance along with its contents are acceptable.</p>
                <p>The next three lines along the black line must appear inside the originPointDistance element since
                    they are directly below and indented from it. The black line indicates they are grouped together and
                    must appear in the order they are given going down the page.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="The latitude and longitude elements">
                <p>The latitude element must be the first thing inside of the originPointDistance element. A latitude
                    only contains one thing: a 'double'. Text without brackets in bold indicates a single piece of data.
                    Anything that matches a generic datatype is acceptable here, and clicking on its link will take you
                    to a description of the datatype. Since this is a 'double', pretty much any numeric value can be given.</p>
                <p>After the latitude element and its 'double' contents, the very similar longitude element must be
                    added to originPointDistance. It is just another element with a 'double' value inside of it.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Generic range definition">
                <p> Finally, there is a link to 'range'. A simple link without any brackets should be replaced with the
                    contents of its 'This consists of' section. To see what must go in the place of the range link,
                    click on it to get to its page. It consists of a unit, min, and max element.</p>
                <p>The unit element links to a deeper page that shows that it must be a complete unit element with the
                    name of a unit of distance inside of it. As such, putting one of the values like KILOMETER or MILE
                    satisfies this condition.</p>
                <p>The min and max elements are very similar to the latitude and longitude elements defined earlier.
                    They are just simple elements with doubles inside of them.</p>
                <p>For this particular example, then, the range link in originPointDistance should be replaced with a
                    unit element, a min element, and a max element.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Putting it all together">
                <p>Combining the results of the previous section, originPointDistance consists of an originPointDistance
                    tag with latitude, longitude, unit, min and max tags inside of it:</p>
                <pre>&lt;originPointDistance&gt; &lt;latitude&gt;35&lt;/latitude&gt;
                    &lt;longitude&gt;-85&lt;/longitude&gt;
                    &lt;unit&gt;DEGREE&lt;/unit&gt; &lt;min&gt;30&lt;/min&gt;
                    &lt;max&gt;90&lt;/max&gt; &lt;/originPointDistance&gt;</pre>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section name="Any number of times">
            <p> This indicates that whatever item is next to this can appear any number of times, from 0 to infinity. So
                if a choice has this next to it, you can use as many of the items in the choice as you want, as many
                times as you want. If it's next to a regular item that item can be left out of the strategy file
                completely, or you can use 16 of them in a row</p>
        </section>
        <section name="At Least Once">
            <p> This indicates the item this is associated with can appear as many times as you want, as long as it
                appears once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="choice">
            <p> A choice says the you can use one of the items inside of it. The items inside of a choice are the ones
                closest to the dashed lined coming out of the choice. If the choice is followed by 'optional' that means
                you can use one of the items inside of it, but you can also leave these out. If choice is followed by
                'at least once' you must select one item out of the choice, but you can also select six items out of the
                choice, or you can select the same item 12 times. Any combination works. If the choice is followed by
                "any number of times" it works like it has optional and at least once on it. You can ignore the choice
                entirely, or you can use the items in it over and over again.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="group">
            <p> This indicates the items inside the group(the ones next to the black vertical line) must appear together
                and in the order given. The group can be 'optional' meaning you can take or leave the whole block. It
                can be 'at least one' meaning you have to have at least one of it, and you can have as many more copies
                after the first that you like. 'any number of times' following it is like having both 'optional' and 'at
                least once'. You can leave it out, or you can have it six times, or you can use it once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="optional">
            <p> If an item has 'optional' showing up after it, you can include it in your SOD strategy file or you can
                leave it out entirely.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
