<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOD - How to Interpret This Consists Of</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="The 'This Consists Of' Section of the Tactics Documentation">
            <p>During startup, SOD validates the structure of the strategy file. From the 'sod'
                element at the root to strings and numbers at the deepest levels of the structure,
                only certain items are allowed. The 'This Consists Of' section of the Tactic
                documentation describes the allowed structure for the entirety of the current
                tactic. If you don't know anything about XML it would be helpful to read our <a
                href="../xmlIntro.html">introduction</a> before reading this document. The
                explanation uses the terminology of XML to explain what the pieces are.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="A Basic Example">
            <p>This the 'This consists of' section of the <a
                    href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html">origin point distance</a> tactic.</p>
            <div id="contained">
                <p> &lt;<a href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html"
                    title="Distance range from a fixed point">originPointDistance</a>&gt; <div>
                        <div id="group"> &lt;latitude&gt;<b>
                                <a href="datatypes/DoubleDatatype.html">double</a>
                            </b>&lt;/latitude&gt; <div/> &lt;longitude&gt;<b>
                                <a href="datatypes/DoubleDatatype.html">double</a>
                            </b>&lt;/longitude&gt; <div/>
                            <a href="base/include/range/range.html" title="A range of lengths">range</a>
                            <div/>
                        </div>
                    </div> &lt;/<a href="event/origin/originPointDistance.html" title="Distance range from a fixed point">originPointDistance</a>&gt;<div/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <section name="The containing originPointDistance tag">
                <p>The first line shows the start tag &lt;originPointDistance&gt; . This
                    means that at this point in the strategy file (ie every place in the 'Places
                    containing this' section) the element originPointDistance along with its
                    contents are acceptable. The next three lines along the black line must appear
                    inside the originPointDistance element since they're directly below and indented
                    from it. The black line indicates they're grouped together and must appear in
                    the order they're given going down the page. </p>
            </section>
            <section name="The latitude and longitude elements">
                <p>So the latitude element must be the first thing inside of the originPointDistance
                    element. latitude only contains one thing, a 'double'. Text without brackets in
                    bold indicates a single piece of data. Here anything that matches a generic
                    datatype is acceptable. To see what qualifies under the umbrella of this
                    datatype, click on its link. Since this is a double, pretty much any numeric
                    value can be given. After the latitude element and its double contents, the very
                    similar longitude element must be added to originPointDistance. It is also just
                    an element with a double value inside of it.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Generic range definition">
                <p> Finally, there is a link to range. A simple link like range without any brackets
                    indicates that the link should be replaced with the 'This consists of' section
                    in the page it links to. So to see what must go in the place of the range link,
                    click on it to get to its page. It consists of a unit, min and max element. The
                    unit element links to a deeper page which in turn shows that it must be a
                    complete unit element with a unit of distance inside of it. So
                    &lt;unit&gt;KILOMETER&lt;/unit&gt; or
                    &lt;unit&gt;MILE&lt;/unit&gt; can replace the unit element in
                    range. The min and max elements are very similar to the latitude and longitude
                    elements defined earlier. They're just a simple element with a double inside of
                    them. So the range link in originPointDistance should be replaced with a unit
                    element, a min element, and a max element.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Putting it all together">
                <p>So taking each of those previous sections, this is telling us that
                    originPointDistance consists of an originPointDistance tag with latitude,
                    longitude, unit, min and max tags inside of it as follows:</p>
                <pre>&lt;originPointDistance&gt;
    &lt;latitude&gt;35&lt;/latitude&gt;
    &lt;longitude&gt;-85&lt;/longitude&gt;
    &lt;unit&gt;DEGREE&lt;/unit&gt;
    &lt;min&gt;30&lt;/min&gt;
    &lt;max&gt;90&lt;/max&gt;
&lt;/originPointDistance&gt;</pre>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section name="Any number of times">
            <p> This indicates that whatever item is next to this can appear any number of times,
                from 0 to infinity. So if a choice has this next to it, you can use as many of the
                items in the choice as you want, as many times as you want. If it's next to a
                regular item that item can be left out of the strategy file completely, or you can
                use 16 of them in a row</p>
        </section>
        <section name="At Least Once">
            <p> This indicates the item this is associated with can appear as many times as you
                want, as long as it appears once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="choice">
            <p> A choice says the you can use one of the items inside of it. The items inside of a
                choice are the ones closest to the dashed lined coming out of the choice. If the
                choice is followed by 'optional' that means you can use one of the items inside of
                it, but you can also leave these out. If choice is followed by 'at least once' you
                must select one item out of the choice, but you can also select six items out of the
                choice, or you can select the same item 12 times. Any combination works. If the
                choice is followed by "any number of times" it works like it has optional and at
                least once on it. You can ignore the choice entirely, or you can use the items in it
                over and over again.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="group">
            <p> This indicates the items inside the group(the ones next to the black vertical line)
                must appear together and in the order given. The group can be 'optional' meaning you
                can take or leave the whole block. It can be 'at least one' meaning you have to have
                at least one of it, and you can have as many more copies after the first that you
                like. 'any number of times' following it is like having both 'optional' and 'at
                least once'. You can leave it out, or you can have it six times, or you can use it once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="optional">
            <p> If an item has 'optional' showing up after it, you can include it in your SOD
                strategy file or you can leave it out entirely.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
