<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOD - Help for Tag Docs</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Any number of times">
            <p> This indicates that whatever item is next to this can appear any number of times,
                from 0 to infinity. So if a choice has this next to it, you can use as many of the
                items in the choice as you want, as many times as you want.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="At Least Once">
            <p> This indicates the item this is associated with can appear as many times as you
                want, as long as it appears once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="choice">
            <p> A choice says the you can use one of the items inside of it. The items inside of a
                choice are the ones closest to the dashed lined coming out of the choice. If the
                choice is followed by 'optional' that means you can use one of the items inside of
                it, but you can also leave these out. If choice is followed by 'at least once' you
                must select one item out of the choice, but you can also select six items out of the
                choice, or you can select the same item 12 times. Any combination works. If the
                choice is followed by "any number of times" it works like it has optional and at
                least once on it. You can ignore the choice entirely, or you can use the items in it
                over and over again.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="group">
            <p> This indicates the items inside the group(the ones next to the black vertical line)
                must appear together and in the order given. The group can be 'optional' meaning you
                can take or leave the whole block. It can be 'at least one' meaning you have to have
                at least one of it, and you can have as many more copies after the first that you
                like. 'any number of times' following it is like having both 'optional' and 'at
                least once'. You can leave it out, or you can have it six times, or you can use it once.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="optional">
            <p> If an item has 'optional' showing up after it, you can include it in your SOD strategy
                file or you can leave it out entirely.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
