<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOD - SOD's Tactic Reference</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Welcome to the SOD Tactic Reference!">
            <p>The tactic reference contains a page for every tactic that can go into SOD. If you
                want to extend and improve your SOD runs, it's the place to find pieces of SOD that
                do what you want.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="What is a tactic?">
            <p>A tactic is a single operation in SOD. A SOD strategy file consists of multiple
                tactics that tell SOD how to gather and process data.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="What's in each tactic's page?">
            <p> Each tactic's page consists of four major sections: a description of the tactic's
                uses, an example of the tactic's structure, an abstract description of the tactic's
                structure, and a list of all of the tactics that contain this tactic. </p>
            <section name="Description">
                <p> Each page starts with the name of the tactic followed by its description. The
                    description contains a general idea of what the tactic does, common usages, and
                    references to other tactics that use this one.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Example">
                <p>The example shows what an instance of this tactic looks like. You can copy the
                    example, paste it in the correct place in a strategy file, and SOD will start
                    using it. It can help to see a base usage of a tactic to modify it for your own purposes.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="This consists of">
                <p>This section describes the exact structure of the current tactic. It's important
                    enough to get its own page explaining it <a href="abstractStructure.html">here</a>.</p>
            </section>
            <section name="Places this can be found">
                <p> This section lists every tactic that contains this tactic. In the case where
                    this is contained in a choice, the items that can be substituted for this are
                    listed as well. </p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section name="How do I find the tactic I want?">
            <p>So you've got a SOD strategy file that does most of what you want, but you need to
                refine the data or add another processing step. How do you find the right tactic to
                insert to get the work done? The menu that runs down the left side of all of the
                Tactic Reference pages consists of links to each of the tactic pages for the major
                steps in SOD's operations broken down by arm. If you can identify the step that
                needs to be refined, just select that one out of the menu and find the appropriate
                tactic. Lets say the events SOD returns past a certain distance aren't worth
                processing. Since the problem is solely with the events, that means the event arm
                needs to be tweaked. After clicking on Origin in the eventArm section of the menu,
                scanning the various pieces that can go there reveals originPointDistance. By adding
                an originPointDistance with a small max distance value to the eventArm keeps SOD
                from processing events that are far away.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
