<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
        <properties>
                <title>SOD - Standing Order for Data</title>
        </properties>
        <body>
                <section name="About SOD">
                        <p class="about">SOD (Standing Order for Data) automates tedious data
                                selection, downloading and routine processing tasks in seismology,
                                shortening the time between idea and science. </p>
                        <p class="about">Users first configure SOD with various subsetters that
                                narrow down the torrent of seismic data available. For example,
                                SOD's event arm allows the user to specify where events occur, how
                                large they are, who reported them, and then to build event more
                                complex and precise expressions using logical AND, OR, and NOT
                                combinations of any of the smaller pieces. This same subsetting
                                process is done for seismic networks in the network arm. The
                                combination of the events that have passed through the event arm and
                                the channels that have been selected by the network arm are then run
                                through the waveform arm. This arm allows the user to specify more
                                subsetting that only makes sense with an event-channel pairing like
                                how far the earthquake is away from a station, the back azimuth, and
                                even the amount of data that various servers have for the pairing.
                                Naturally, each of these pieces can be combined in logical
                                operations like the event and network arms. After all of this
                                subsetting has whittled the data down to the interesting stuff, the
                                waveform processors perform various transformations on the data in
                                sequence. So several processors can be stacked up to filter the
                                data, remove the mean, and any other conceivable action. </p>
                        <p class="about">Please read the <a href="walkthrough.html">walkthrough</a>
                                document for an simple tutorial using SOD to get SAC data from the
                                IRIS DMC.</p>
                </section>
                <section name="News">
                        <table id="entry">
                                <th>13 May 2004</th>
                                <tr>
                                        <td>
                                                <p>The first beta of SOD 2.0 is available <a href="download.html">here.</a>  More beta releases should follow in the coming weeks.</p>
                                        </td>
                                </tr>
                        </table>
                </section>
        </body>
</document>
