<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOD - Download</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Download SOD">
            <p> SOD is distributed as either a tar file or a zip file. Both contain
                identical content, so you only need to download the one that is most
                convenient for you. See the <a href="install.html">INSTALL</a> document for an
                explanation of the contents. </p>
            <p>
                <b>Current Release:</b> Sod 2.0 RC1 <a class="download" href="rc1/sod-2.0rc1.tar">TAR</a>
                <a class="download" href="rc1/sod-2.0rc1.zip">ZIP</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 29 September 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 RC1:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>ETOPO information on map</li>
                <li>Detail in strategy file documentation</li>
                <li>removeDatabase property works properly</li>
                <li>Several new editor widgets</li>
                <li>Several bug fixes</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Previous Releases">
        <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 8 <a class="download" href="beta8/sod-2.0beta8_3.tar">TAR</a>
                <a class="download" href="beta8/sod-2.0beta8_2.zip">ZIP</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 29 July 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 8:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Safeguards for minor hiccups from the event server</li>
                <li>Safeguards for minor hiccups from the seismogram server</li>
                <li>New strategy file reference</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 7 <a class="download" href="beta7/sod-beta7.tar">TAR</a>
                <a class="download" href="beta7/sod-beta7.zip">ZIP</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 09 July 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 7:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Table sorting works in Safari</li>
                <li>Various improvements were made to the layout of the status pages.</li>
                <li>Loading and saving files in the editor now correctly respects the location given
                    to it.</li>
                <li>New legacy execution processor</li>
                <li>New linear distance from a point magnitude subsetter</li>
                <li>Improvements were made to the robustness of the connection to the network server.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 6 <a class="download" href="beta6/sod-beta6.tar">TAR</a>
                <a class="download" href="beta6/sod-beta6.zip">ZIP</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 15 June 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 6:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>SOD's sh scripts work on Solaris now.</li>
                <li>Save now works on config files loaded automatically by the editor.</li>
                <li>Links to the config file and its HTML version are now correct in the menus.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 5 <a class="download" href="beta5/sod-beta5.tar">TAR</a>
                <a class="download" href="beta5/sod-beta5.zip">ZIP</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 10 June 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 5:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>This was a minor bug fix release.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 4 <a class="download" href="beta4/sod-beta4.tar">Download</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 09 June 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 4:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>SOD now uses the at most once/at least once property to determine if it should
                    reopen or permanently close event channel pairs that were being processed when a
                    run died. </li>
                <li>Seismograms displayed after running through the response gain processor are now
                    correctly labelled and scaled.</li>
                <li>This release marks the introduction of the motion vector channel grouper.
                    Instead of just grouping channels on their orientation codes, SOD can use a
                    series of rules to determine which channels go together in the motion vector arm.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Sod 2.0 Beta 3 <a class="download" href="beta3/sod-beta3.tar">Download</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 31 May 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 3:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>DSML file output is vastly improved. It requires 10 times less memory and is twice as fast!</li>
                <li>There is a new postEventWait event subsetter. Check out <a href="realtime.html">these
                        realtime considerations</a> to see how it works.</li>
                <li>SOD will no longer retry event channel pairs until the end of time.</li>
                <li>SOD will warn you if you're running a new version of SOD on an old database and
                    if you've changed config files between runs on a single database.</li>
                <li>There is a new removeEventDuplicate subsetter that will keep SOD from processing duplicate
                    event entries.</li>
                <li>-demo flag starts SOD on tutorial.xml</li>
            </ul>
            <p> Sod 2.0 Beta 2 <a class="download" href="beta2/sod-beta2.tar">Download</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 24 May 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 2:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>An HTML version of the config file is created by the status system.</li>
                <li>HTML view of waveforms sorted by stations</li>
                <li>All columns in the tables can be sorted</li>
                <li>Can now query the DMC's archive</li>
            </ul>
            <p> Sod 2.0 Beta 1 <a class="download" href="beta1/sod-beta1.tar">Download</a>
            </p>
            <p>Released 13 May 2004</p>
            <p>Changes in 2.0 Beta 1:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>There are none. This is the first beta.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
