<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
        <properties>
                <author>Philip Crotwell</author>
                <title>SOD Installation</title>
        </properties>
        <body>
                <section name="Installing SOD">
                        <p>
                        SOD is currently distributed in tar and zip formats, both contain
                        identical content. After <a href="download.html">downloading</a>
                        the most recent version, untaring or unzipping it will
                        result in a directory structure like the following:
                        <ul>
                                <li><tt>sod-2.0</tt><ul>
                                                <li><tt>bin</tt> - scripts for running sod and the sod editor</li>
                                                <li><tt>docs</tt> - documentation in html</li>
                                                <li><tt>examples</tt> - strategy files for use as starting points</li>
                                                <li><tt>lib</tt> - library files used by sod</li>
                                        </ul>
                                </li>
                        </ul>
                        </p>
                </section>
                <section name="SOD_HOME">
                    <p>
                        SOD is effectively installed at this point, and you can certainly
                        run it from within the <tt>sod</tt> directory with <tt>./bin/sod.sh</tt>. However, SOD's scripts
                        use the SOD_HOME environment variable
                        to find SOD's libraries. In order to run sod from another
                        directory, you can either set SOD_HOME as an environmental
                        variable or in the scripts in the <tt>bin</tt> directory.
                        Changing the scripts is the recommended method.
                    </p>
                    <p>To set it in the script, cd into the bin directory.
                        If you're on a Unix like platform, open up sod.sh in a text editor.
                        On Windows, open up sod.bat for editing. You will also need to edit sodeditor.sh or sodeditor.bat.
                        Near the beginning of these files is the <b>SOD_HOME</b> variable.
                        It's currently set to '../' so you can run SOD from the <tt>sod</tt> directory.
                        Set the value to the path to SOD's directory. For example, if SOD was
                        installed in <tt>/usr/local/sod-2.0</tt>, then you would do this for unix:<br/>
                        <tt>SOD_HOME=/usr/local/sod-2.0</tt><br/>
                        and this for windows:<br/>
                        <tt>set SOD_HOME=c:\usr\local\sod-2.0</tt><br/>
                        The scripts are smart enough to append lib or bin as needed.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                      Now SOD can be run from any
                        directory, which makes segregating results from runs easier.  Once you've
                        done that SOD is officially installed. If you're not too worn out,
                        now might be a good time to go on to the
                        <a href="walkthrough.html">strategy file via editor</a> section to
                                see various neat things SOD can do.
                    </p>
                </section>
        </body>
</document>
