<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
        <properties>
                <author>Philip Crotwell</author>
                <title>SOD Installation</title>
        </properties>
        <body>
                <section name="Installing SOD">
                        <p> SOD is currently distributed in tar and zip formats. Both contain the
                                same content, but we want to keep everyone happy. After <a
                                href="download.html">downloading</a> the most recent version of the
                                zip or the tar, whichever you please, unpack it with the tool of
                                your choice. This will unpack something in a directory structure
                                like the following:</p>
                        <ul>
                                <li>SOD <ul>
                                                <li>bin</li>
                                                <li>lib</li>
                                                <li>docs</li>
                                        </ul>
                                </li>
                        </ul>
                        <p> If all of these things came out of the distribution, you should probably set SOD_HOME now.  SOD's scripts use the SOD_HOME variable to determine where SOD has been installed on your local system so SOD can find its libraries.  You can set SOD_HOME as an enviromental variable or in the run script you're going to use for SOD.  To set it in the run script cd into the bin directory.  If you're on a Unix like platform, open up sod.sh in the text editor of your choice.  On Windows, open up sod.bat for editing.  Near the beginning of these files is the SOD_HOME variable.  It's currently set to '../' so you can run SOD from the SOD directory unpacked from the tar.  Set the value to the directory SOD was unpacked to from the tar in your local filesystem.  Now SOD can be run from any location which makes segrating results from runs easier.  Once you've done that SOD is officiallly installed. If you're not too worn out
                                by the heavy lifting involved so far now might be a good
                                time to go on to the <a href="walkthrough.html">walkthrough</a> to
                                see various neat things SOD can do. </p>
                </section>
        </body>
</document>
