<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Philip Crotwell</author>
    <title>SOD's properties</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="SOD's Properties">
<p>
Sod has several parameters that can be set at run time in the xml config file.  These are set in the properties element which is the first element in the sod element of sod's config file.  
</p>
<b>Normal Properties</b>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;Name of the property&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;Value this property will have&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<p>
Most properties are like this.  The name element specifies which property you're setting, and the value sets the value of that property.
</p>
<b>Unit based properties</b>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.unit&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;week&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.value&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<p>The other type of property isused to specify a unit based value like the above. This property is setting the amount of time sod waits for events to show up after the end date specified in the event arm, or the event lag.  These properties require two property elements in the properties element.  The first has a name element with the property's name as a value with .unit appended to it.  The value element's value is the time's unit.  The second property element has a name lement value of the properties name with .value appended to it.  The value element's value is the number of the units specifed in the previous element to use.  This example property is setting the event lag to be one week.
</p>
<b>Acceptable units</b>
<ul>
	<li>second</li>
	<li>minute</li>
	<li>hour</li>
	<li>day</li>
	<li>week</li>
	<li>fortnight</li>
</ul>
<subsection name="Run Properties">
<br/>
<b>sod.start.RunName</b>
<p>
This property sets the current sod run name.  It shows up in the html output for the run.  The following example would name the run "Test Run". If this property isn't set, sod uses the default value, "Your Sod".  No insult intended. 
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.start.RunName&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;Test Run&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</source>
<br/>
<b>sod.start.StatusBaseDirectory</b>
<p>
StatusBaseDirectory tells sod where to put all of its html status pages.  The example here places all of the status files in c:/status.  If this isn't set, any status pages generated will go in a directory called status in the directory in which sod is run.
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.start.StatusBaseDirectory&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;c:/status&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</source>
<br/>
<b>sod.start.ReopenEvents</b>
<p>
If ReopenEvents' value is true, sod will reprocess all of the events in its existing database again.  If its value is false, it will act like whatever caused it to exit with the current database intact was merely a brief interruption and contine processing events from where it left off.
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.start.ReopenEvents&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</source>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Event Arm Properties">
<br/>
<b>sod.event.QueryIncrement</b>
<p>
The event QueryIncrement controls how many days of events sod asks for per query to the event server.  For optimal performace, set this value to the smallest amount that will reliably return events for your particular event arm configuration.  This particular query increment gets one week of events at a time.  The default query increment is one week.
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.QueryIncrement.unit&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;week&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.QueryIncrement.value&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<br/>
<b>sod.event.Lag</b>
<p>
Event lag controls how long after the final date in the event arm configuration sod will wait for tardy events to arrive.  For example, if the catalog you're using usually takes a week to get events ready, set this value to a week.  Sod will wait for that long after the last event time you've asked for for new events to arrive, but it won't get events that have occured after the last time you've set on the event arm.  This example tells sod to wait for two fortnights, or four weeks, for events to show up.  The default lag is one week.
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.unit&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;fortnight&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.value&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;2&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<br/>
<b>sod.event.RefreshInterval</b>
<p>
The event refresh interval is the amount of time sod waits between queries to the event server once it has caught up to real time.  When we write the main sod documentation, the fact that this property is settable is going to be removed and the fact that the default value is 10 minutes will be mentioned in the docs.  
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.RefreshInterval.unit&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;minute&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.RefreshInterval.value&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;10&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
