<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Philip Crotwell</author>
    <title>SOD's properties</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="SOD's Properties">
<p>
Sod has several parameters that can be set at run time in the xml config file.  These are set in the properties element which is the first element in the sod element of sod's config file.  
</p>
<b>Normal Properties</b>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;Name of the property&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;Value this property will have&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<p>
Most properties are like this.  The name element specifies which property you're setting, and the value sets the value of that property.
</p>
<b>Unit based properties</b>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.unit&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;week&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.event.Lag.value&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;property&gt;
</source>
<p>The other type of property isused to specify a unit based value like the above. This property is setting the amount of time sod waits for events to show up after the end date specified in the event arm, or the event lag.  These properties require two property elements in the properties element.  The first has a name element with the property's name as a value with .unit appended to it.  The value element's value is the time's unit.  The second property element has a name lement value of the properties name with .value appended to it.  The value element's value is the number of the units specifed in the previous element to use.  This example property is setting the event lag to be one week.
</p>
<b>Acceptable units</b>
<ul>
	<li>second</li>
	<li>minute</li>
	<li>hour</li>
	<li>day</li>
	<li>week</li>
	<li>fortnight</li>
</ul>
<subsection name="Run Properties">
<br/>
<b>sod.start.RunName</b>
<p>
This property sets the current sod run name.  It shows up in the html output for the run.  The following example would name the run "Test Run".
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.start.RunName&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;Test Run&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</source>
<br/>
<b>sod.start.StatusBaseDirectory</b>
<p>
StatusBaseDirectory tells sod where to put all of its html status pages.  The example here places all of the status files in c:/status
</p>
<source>
&lt;property&gt;
	&lt;name&gt;sod.start.StatusBaseDirectory&lt;/name&gt;
	&lt;value&gt;c:/status&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
</source>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
