<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author>Philip Crotwell</author>
    <title>SOD Installation</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Take off your shoes, wiggle your toes and take a walk on the SOD">
<p>
We shall assume that you have successfully downloaded and extracted SOD from
its tar or zip file. If not please have a look at the
<a href="install.html">installation</a> document.
</p>
<p>
Slide into the SOD directory, where you should see various files and subdirectories.
Start up the GUI editor, by running <code>./bin/editor.sh</code> or <code>bin\editor.bat</code>.
The editor should start with the tutorial configuration preloaded. This is
contained within the editor, so there is no need to worry about messing anything
up as it can be reset by choosing ***TODO*** from the ***TODO*** menu. You will
see several tabs which cover the various sectios of a SOD run. We will cover each
in turn.
</p>
<section name="Event">
<p>
The Event tab, also known as the Event Arm, selects which events are of interest.
The tutorial configuration file by default gets events from the IRIS Event server
from anywhere in the world with magnitude greater than 6 during January of 2003.
These values can be changed and SOD can do quite a bit more things, but this is
a minimal set paramters. One subtle point is that a single real earthquake will
be in multiple catalogs within the DMC's database. Because there is currently
no way to automatically group these related origins into a single event based on
the information that the DMC has, these origins each appear in separate events.
So, it is usually wise to pick a particular catalog to avoid duplicate
processing. The default here is the PREF catalog from the DMC. PREF is not a true
catalog, but rather somethign that the DMC Event server understands as the "best"
catalog depending on the time range. The weeklies, or WHDF, catalog from the
NEIC is another common one for historical data and if you
are doing a SOD run and want near real time data, then you probably want to
use FINGER catalog as that has a short delay from earthquake occuring to the
location being in the FINGER catalog.
</p>
<p>
After the query to the remote event server, we have our events locally and
could do some subsetting based on the origin, but for the tutorial we will
assume all of these events are fine. Just to make running
sod a little more interesting, we will include an event processor. This one just
prints out a line every time an event arrives. This finishes the event arm.
</p>
<p>
Feel free to modify any of these values to customize your search. Be aware that
some servers may not have data for all types of earthquakes, and it is possible
to make choices that result in no data matching. Mistakes are the best way to
learn, so click away!
</p>
</section>

<section name="Network">
<p>
The Network tab is the other side of the coin, once you have earthquakes, you must
pick stations in order to ask for data.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Waveform">
<p>
</p>
</section>

</section>
</body>
</document>
